<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Skillet</title><link>skillet.gastove.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="skillet.gastove.com/feeds/ross-donaldson.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Mar 2014 00:00:00 -0800</lastBuildDate><item><title>Shake, Pour, Sip: an Overview of Cocktail Making Basics</title><link>skillet.gastove.com/2014-02-16_shake_pour_sip_an_overview.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Go to a cocktail bar -- a fancy one. Watch the tender make your drink. Now go to a different bar and watch again. Maybe hit a third.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many ways did you just see a canister full of liquor and ice get shaken?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you asked your bartender about how they made the drink, you probably got a lot of... "information." You now know not to bruise your gin, whatever that means, and an explanation about why you should always set your citrus on fire over a drink; you've probably gotten at least one diatribe about ice cubes, another about the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; origin of the Martini, and who-knows-what else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look: I'm not trying to suggest that cocktails are skill-free to make -- far from it. Bartending is a craft. Making a good cocktail requires attention and care and good technique. My assertion is this: with a clear head about how to execute a couple of basics, you can clear up a lot of what's bad about most mixed drinks and start learning about what you like. I also assert that the waters have been muddied by a combination of superstition, lore, and "we've always done it this way so we'd better make up a story to explain it" issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further adieu, I present my very own Cocktail Technique 101.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Measuring&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the bit of bartending misinformation that rankles me the most:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real bartenders just know how much to pour. Measuring ingredients is, therefore, the sign of an amateur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, in a word, wrong. There are only two reasons to value just-pouring over measuring: measuring is marginally slower; if you skip measuring, you can &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AMXkiX9Hr_o"&gt;flair bartend&lt;/a&gt;. There is nothing in the world wrong with being behind the bar at a nightclub and needing to pour twelve thousand long-island iced teas for a sea of glitteratti. It's also not, I argue, the most reliable way to make consistent craft cocktails. Put another way: I measure my ingredients, all of my favorite bars measure their ingredients, and you should measure your ingredients, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll be surprised how much mystery this clears up. Drink too sweet? Cut the sugar in half. Martini too dry, or not dry enough? Produce a consistent, reproducible modification, then &lt;em&gt;write it down&lt;/em&gt; so you can remember what you did. Making a great cocktail has nothing to do with counting seconds from a speed pour; it has a lot to do with knowing that a good Manhattan base is 2 ounces of rye and 0.75 ounces of sweet vermouth, and knowing that's exactly how much of each ingredient is in your glass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also worth considering: cocktails are one of the only things you'll ever make in a kitchen that can be &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the same every time you make them. A bottle of Maker's Mark is just shy of certain to taste like every other bottle of Maker's Mark you ever buy, ever. This means that you, the bartender, have nearly perfect control over every variable in your drink. If you have reliable measuring, then everything you change happens on purpose. Now my friend: that is bartending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suggestion: measure with &lt;a href="http://www.oxo.com/p-510-mini-angled-measuring-cup.aspx"&gt;one of these&lt;/a&gt;. They aren't particularly pretty, but they're cheap as can be and incredibly easy to use well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Combining&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Shaken or stirred?" is a surprisingly easy question. It goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would you like to be able to see through the drink you just made? Then stir it. If not, or if it doesn't matter, shake the bazoley out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...that's it. You're done. Well, okay -- there are a few edge cases, like the Brandy Alexander, where you &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; shake to give the drink the texture that makes it special (ditto anything with egg whites). But all of the edge cases pass the first and most important test: is it clear? In practice, "clear" means "contains neither fruit juice nor milk nor eggs." Martini? Stir that -- you'll get a crystalline drink to present in your best stemware. Mai Tai? Shake it like... like...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well shake it like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measure your ingredients in to a pint glass.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dump a bunch of ice in to your Boston Shaker (the metal cup you always see bartenders use).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pour the liquid in to the metal cup, then put the pint glass in to the shaker to form a complete vessel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thump the butt of the pint glass, soundly, with your open palm or fist. You need to make a seal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick this up and shake it. Shake it as hard as you can. There is no right or wrong way to do this, so long as you are shaking with as much violence as you can muster. Seriously -- fancy patterns and weird rhythms are all stagecraft. What you want to do is shake this thing like something terrible will happen if you don't shake hard enough. I like to place a palm on each end of the capsule, because I feel more confident when I can hold both halves together. Remember: rapidly cooling the inside of this canister is going to reduce the volume of the ingredients and air, as well as causing the metal shaker to contract -- all of which work to make the seal you're going to be relying on to keep the drink &lt;em&gt;inside&lt;/em&gt; the shaker. This means: don't dawdle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shake until the metal gets unconfortably cold to touch and/or frost forms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To open: place the shaker down on the counter, metal half down. Place one hand along the side of the canister and hold it firmly. With your other hand, smack the outisde of the metal shaker at about the place the pint glass is stuck in to it. If you do this right, you should hear the sucking sound of a vacuum being released, and the top of the shaker should come off easily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stirring is considerably easier and more peaceful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put ice in a pint glass&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measure your ingredients over the ice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stir with a bar spoon until everything is really cold.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel pretty smug you aren't shaking this thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Strain&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is gonna sound silly, but here it is: when I get a cocktail in a bar, and I take a sip of it, the first thing that hits me is how well strained it was -- &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; if the drink was a) shaken and b) served up. Shaking generates tiny chips of ice, and there simply isn't a Hawthorne strainer on this Earth that will remove them. Instead, an incautiously strained drink will have a layer of ice flakes that float on top of the drink, bump against your lips as you sip, spoil the texture of the cocktail, and slowly dilute it too far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avoiding this problem is ridiculously simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did you stir your drink? Strain by placing a Julep Spoon down in to the pint glass. Done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was the drink shaken? Place a Hawthorne strainer on top of your shaker. Now, pour the drink through a small, fine sieve. If the drink is thick -- an Alexander or a Sour, for instance -- you can speed the drinks passage through the strainer by tapping the strainer with the end of the shaker.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Accessorize&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By now, you should have something delicious in a glass. This is good news! You're almost there. Last thing you need is to make sure the whole works is tied together. Let's talk trimmings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that many drinks don't need a damn thing, and as you make your own cocktails, you should ask about what your final addition is really &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; for the drink. Here's a first rule: aesthetics are very important, but I prefer things that add a flavor or aroma that completes the drink. An Old Fashioned &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; a little sweet orange flavor? Not as good. On the other hand, I'll drink an un-garnished Martini. The flavor of a Sazerac is so tight and dense that I think a little citrus zest is crucial. A Remember the Maine gets cherries because they are nice to eat -- by the time you've made the drink, it should be so infused with cherry-ness that the cherries take flavor from the &lt;em&gt;drink&lt;/em&gt;, not the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a word I've been trying not to say: "garnish." "Garnish" brings to mind sprigs of parsley -- little piles of dross that get added just for the visual appeal. Certainly, I've had plenty of garnished cocktails. Rum drinks, in particular, often come with "flags" of fruit -- essentially a fruit side-salad on a skewer -- that I'd be hard-pressed to say I "enjoy." The visual appeal of your drink &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; very important. My philosophy is: achieve pleasing aesthetics with good serving glasses and well-chosen &lt;em&gt;accoutrement&lt;/em&gt; (straws, etc); consider garnish an ingredient, and like any other ingredient, only use what truly improves the flavor of the drink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whew. Okay. Rant done -- I feel better, thanks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's talk about using zest: this is another place where you're going to see a thousand different techniques. There are only a couple things to make sure of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use fresh citrus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do your zesting over the drink. You'll be surprised how much citrus oil is released as you cut the fruit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you're making a fancy shape from your zest, do that over the drink, too. Always find some way to squeeze or stretch the zest over the beverage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the zest around the edge of the glass before settling it in to the drink.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How fancy you want to get with shaping/skewering/whatever-ing your zest is entirely a question of preference and aesthetics. Me? I use a sharp vegetable peeler to cut a wide swath of zest -- I find it attractive and easy to handle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last point: don't drop small things loose in to your drinks. Yes, I know, this is done all the time -- a lone cherry sitting in the bottom of your Manhattan, which was probably served in a martini glass. Personally, I can't stand having something that isn't ice rattling around in my cocktail. If the drink is served up, I don't want to choke on some loose bit of Stuff; if the drink is served over, I don't want to have to go fishing if I decide I want to eat whatever was dropped in there. The moral of this story is: put your cherry/olive/onion/candied ginger/salted plum/what-have-you on a toothpick or skewer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;In Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solid technique is the cornerstone of improvisation -- as true in playing jazz as it is in dancing as it is in bartending. Firm up your technique, then see where you can go. Which whiskey do you like best in a Manhattan? Which gin is right for a Martini versus a G&amp;amp;T? You can figure this stuff out once your technique is reliable -- and that's where making cocktails gets good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now what are you waiting for? Go make a drink!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Ross Donaldson</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 01 Mar 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-03-01:skillet.gastove.com/2014-02-16_shake_pour_sip_an_overview.html</guid><category>cocktails</category><category>techniques</category></item><item><title>Bubba Donaldson's School of Campfire Cookin'</title><link>skillet.gastove.com/2014-02-16_bubba_donaldsons_school_of_campfire.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When I was little, my father taught me how to cook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...okay, that's not strictly true. Or even... approximately true. My father is an incredible man; I have no right to his story, except at the intersection of my own. And the truth of the matter is that I was taught the 'how's and 'what's of cooking by my mother. My mother taught me young and thoroughly that cooking is a show of care, among the more genuine ways to tell somebody, "have a seat, you're loved here." And from my mother, I got a second part, too. To quote her directly, "sometimes I just have to sit back and make 'yummy' noises." Indirectly quoting now: "I love you, and this is going to taste &lt;em&gt;awesome&lt;/em&gt;."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know, though, that's an intersection between my father and mother -- one of the rare ones they shared, though unintentionally. While my mother loves food, my father is less than excited by it, most of the time. And yet: when my mother wound up with the lion's share of custody over my sister and I, my father ate pizza until sick of it, cooked mac'n'cheese until he never wanted to touch it again, even took us out to -- I'm not making this up -- Red Lobster. Fun facts: my father doesn't much like pizza, and probably hasn't had either mac'n'cheese or Red Lobster since the last time my sister or I forced them on him. But he &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; us, and he wanted us to eat something &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; liked, and he put us first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me until my twenties to figure that out. The guy was so hellbent on seeing my sister and I eat something we liked for dinner that we (or at least I) never caught on to his preferences. Same message as my mom; totally different packaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The closest my father came to teaching me to cook was a series of recipes he'd declare from time to time. He called them-- wait, no, we need a better setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you know my father? Probably not -- he's shy as can be, and like I said, his story isn't mine to tell you. I'll tell you that he's quiet, an intellectual, plays bridge very well. Visualize me, but thinner and a half-foot shorter. Tweed jacket, sweater vest, a cigar. North of twenty published novels. His idea of "roughing it" is "a condo with not very many restaurants near by."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And he used to "teach" me recipes from Bubba Donaldson's School of Campfire Cookin'. Here's my favorite:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Bubba Donaldson's Camp Fire Scrambled Eggs:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crush eggs in your fists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hold your fists in the fire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right? I love these things. Maybe it's a little tricky to tell what I learned here, though. Let's try another one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Bubba Donaldson's How to Boil Water at Camp:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oh, it'll boil.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here am I, as enthusiastic an eater as I know. And here is my father, who would have cheerfully stopped eating years ago if he could. We're alike in so many ways -- a taste for Wagner and long words and shirts in solid colors. Food is one of the few places where we are from each other distant, and I think we feel that acutely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next week I'm going to turn thirty, I've decided -- it's about time. My father is coming to town, and like always, he wants to take me out to dinner. This might be the most challenging thing we do together; food isn't something we can easily share. The mechanics are different, I now see; when I cook for a person, part of the joy is in the sharing -- while from my father, the gift of food is more discrete, like a book or a watch or a TV. And we butt heads. My favorite dinner parties are a delight to every participant, while to him the whole point of the gift he wants to give is that this meal should be what &lt;em&gt;I and only I&lt;/em&gt; want. If I ask him what he'd like best, we're already at odds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, this core remains true: damn does that man love me, and he wants to feed me to show it, and I get kinda choked up about it when I think about it too long. Because when I was little, my father helped to teach me to speak love through food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love you too, Dad.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Ross Donaldson</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-02-16:skillet.gastove.com/2014-02-16_bubba_donaldsons_school_of_campfire.html</guid><category>Thoughts</category><category>Food</category><category>Father</category><category>Love</category></item><item><title>Eat as you'd like to Live. (Well, I hope.)</title><link>skillet.gastove.com/2013-09-11_eat_as_youd_like_to.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I'd like to take a moment to articulate two or three points of philosophy. I probably think as much as I eat, and I eat better than I cook, and I cook better than most; it should surprise you little that I think a lot about how much I like eating, and what I like to eat, and why. Turns out I also like feeding people, and dear reader, that includes you. You're not here right now. This post will have to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to tell you a thing or two about how I believe people should cook and be fed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or at least, how I like best to cook, eat, and be fed. I'm a little peculiar, after all; I like a surprising amount of fat in my diet. I eat, broadly speaking, very few carbohydrates, simple or complex -- so few that it took four different very smart coaches to convince me I had to eat at least &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; carbs if I wanted to stop feeling like hell at CrossFit.&lt;sup id="fnref:cf"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:cf" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Some of my very favorite people aren't actually in love with my default mode of cooking, which tends to be... erh, rustic. Foods with a certain butter-backed fortitude. Foods for building walls and being a little ruddy with wine and laughing 'til it's hard to sit upright. Food-- well, you get the idea. Point is, I eat my way, and it will never fly to feed my food to vegans, bless 'em, or the lactose intolerant, or even vegetarians. I'm too omnivorous. Even the gluten-free are in peril.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first rule is, &lt;strong&gt;eat in your own way&lt;/strong&gt;. Are there ways of eating that are terribly unhealthy? Well, yes, and I wish nobody did them. Eating in your own way can be complex and a little thorny, but to paraphrase Evelyn Beatrice Hall:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I disapprove of what you eat, but I will defend to the death your right to eat it.&lt;sup id="fnref:hall"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:hall" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the topic of health, I'd like to touch briefly on the even more awkward point of research -- because there's a lot of it and it's a mess. I spent a while trying to (ahem) "summarize the research" for this post, and frankly: AUGH. A quick Googling on the topic of your choice will support any conclusion you'd care to come to. A traipse through Google Scholar will leave you... well, that depends on who you are, but I found it slow going. You could go &lt;a href="http://hells-ditch.com/2012/08/archaeologists-officially-declare-collective-sigh-over-paleo-diet/"&gt;paeleo&lt;/a&gt;, of course, or embrace the Weston A. Price appoach&lt;sup id="fnref:weston"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:weston" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or you could try rule number two: &lt;strong&gt;eat how you feel &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not as simple as saying it, because humans are wired with a problematic love of Absolute Crap. To celebrate this love, we've built rather a fortress of Crap between ourselves and what I'll broadly call 'good food'. This is more or less my only conviction about what, in an absolute sense, is good food: with a few exceptions, you could conceivably make it at home. And I mean &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the benighted thing you're considering chewing on. There is not one person who can make a Big Mac at home, and that is for the best -- but we can most of us make a damn fine hamburger, given the want and the resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to Crap: my own relationship with more-or-less cutting refined sugar from my diet was not one of immediately feeling lovely. Instead, I went through something very much like withdrawal, and periodically I Jones for sugar but good. Y'know what though? I feel lovely. On a day-to-day basis I feel &lt;em&gt;worlds&lt;/em&gt; better. It took some experimentation and a little time, but oh &lt;em&gt;man&lt;/em&gt; has it been worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rule three is somewhat of a tag-along to rule two, and it goes &lt;strong&gt;eat how you move, move how you eat&lt;/strong&gt;. When I'm CrossFit-ing regularly, I regularly eat four or five &lt;em&gt;thousand&lt;/em&gt; calories in a day. That's pretty stupid. I mean, not stupid-stupid -- it's conceptually ridiculous to me. On Monday I ate, over the course of two meals, an entire roasted chicken. I mean, what? Correspondingly, I go run the hell around. I have a taste for goopy French cheeses and chicken liver pate; accordingly, I try to eat a diet that can sustain those things. And when I slow down, I eat less -- I listen to my stomach and if I do it carefully I can hear it say "stop, you're good." Five meals a day become three again become a weekend with only four good meals in it and some snacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's one last rule, and it's simple: &lt;strong&gt;everybody deserves good food&lt;/strong&gt;. Everybody. Your house-guests, whoever they are, however odd their diets may seem to you. Your relatives. That aunt -- the one with the "family traditions" that all involve molding food into shapes. You. Everybody. Deserves. Good. Food. I get flustered and wordless when I try and talk about how much love goes in to my cooking, but it's lots, and at the root of it is a desire to &lt;em&gt;nourish well this special human&lt;/em&gt;. Food sustains you. Food motivates you. Your stomach is, in a very literal way, your &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/23/health/23gut.html?pagewanted=all"&gt;second brain&lt;/a&gt;. The first brain runs on the work of the second; the second relies on materials of quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eat like you want to live: well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:cf"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protip: they were not wrong.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:cf" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:hall"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also think its important to remember that not everybody gets to pick their diet. Eating what you'd like to -- what you'd &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; like to -- is a privilege. This means fighting for better food for &lt;em&gt;everybody&lt;/em&gt;. It also means not beating up people who don't have the privilege of dietary choice, for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; reason.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The actual quote is, "I disapprove of what you say, but I will defend to the death your right to say it." It is typically credited to Voltaire, but &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evelyn_Beatrice_Hall"&gt;this is incorrect&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:hall" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:weston"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weston_A._Price_Foundation"&gt;Wikipedia Article&lt;/a&gt; on this is quite good; scroll to the bottom for critiques.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:weston" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Ross Donaldson</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>tag:,2013-09-11:skillet.gastove.com/2013-09-11_eat_as_youd_like_to.html</guid><category>Thoughts</category><category>Opinions</category><category>Food</category></item><item><title>Chicken and Dumplings, Whatever You Do</title><link>skillet.gastove.com/2013-09-09_chicken_and_dumplings_whatever_you.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm prone to carbs. I've untangled them from my diet here and there, but it's a push and a pull. I skip one to eat the next, budgeting a place in my diet for sourdough, good beer, tagliatele. Day to day, I eat well, I feel well, am happy and healthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, I'm not healthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a set of foods I go to when my health wavers. Mostly, they make me feel worse, so I try to avoid them. (After all, what could be better for sickness than drinking ginger ale until you're ill from sugar?) There are three exceptions -- foods I can eat and recover, get healthier. Spicy chicken soup with noodles. Grilled cheese on sourdough with tomato soup. And the apex of comfort foods: stewed chicken with parsley dumplings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a family recipe; the notes I have from my mother came from her mother, equal parts anecdote and measures. The idea is simple: a chicken is cut into pieces, floured, browned in fat, removed. Onions go in to the fat, then the chicken again but now with sage and cider vinegar and stock. As it cooks, you make a simple batter of flour and milk, made lighter and brighter with parsley. The dumplings cook floating on top of the broth and the chicken, the lid on tight. My sister and I between us ate so many dumplings that the recipe contains a note advising a triple batch, almost more dumplings than you can fit in a pot with a chicken. We still used to run out of dumplings before meat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are so few ways this can go wrong. Here are all of them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use an electric mixer on the dumplings. You'll knock them silly; they'll fight back by being impossible to chew.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use crappy chicken stock. Seriously, if you don't have your own on hand (I frequently don't), get a jar of Better than Bouillon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cook it too long.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...that's it. The dumpling ingredients are less flexible than those of the stewed chicken, but you can swap parsley for about any other fresh herb you like (sage is very good), or you can omit it entirely. You can use more onion, add garlic, leave both out all together, more vinegar or less, bay or no bay. I grew up eating dumplings made with vegetable shortening; I prefer making them with lard or schmaltz. It's remarkably easy going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent the weekend sick with stomach things and today I craved Real Food -- something I could eat and feel better, something easy to digest. I did the worst job I could making chicken and dumplings. I forgot the onion entirely; my chicken was frozen solid; I put the pieced chicken in with the whole frozen chicken so it all cooked at different speeds. But I didn't do any of the three mistakes above, and you know what?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My dinner was &lt;em&gt;delicious&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Stewed Chicken:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 whole chicken, cut in to pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 onion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 teaspoons sage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup cider vinegar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 cups chicken stock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 bay leaf&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup white flour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oil or fat for low-temperature frying&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Dumplings:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 cups white flour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 teaspoons baking powder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup parsley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 tablespoons shortening, very cold&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 cup milk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll need: a single large pot. I use a big ol' Dutch oven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Directions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your chicken comes whole, cut it in to pieces -- legs, each in two pieces, wings, breasts removed from the back and split.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your oil: use anything you can fry the chicken pieces in. I like schmaltz best for this. Heat it in the pot on something medium-ish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While the oil heats, toss the chicken pieces in salt, black pepper, and the quarter-cup flour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fry the chicken pieces in the oil; don't crowd them. Brown the pieces, pulling them out and resting them as needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slice the onion into thick rings. Toss it into the fat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once the onion is soft, add the chicken back in, along with the stock, vinegar, sage, and bay.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simmer. I give mine twentyish minutes of gentle simmering before I leap back into action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time for dumplings! Combine everything but the shortening and milk. Your herbs should be chopped; I go for something just north of 'fine'.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Toss the shortening in; using your fingertips, rub the fat into the dry ingredients until it looks like coarse meal. This takes very little time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using a spoon, stir the milk in to the dumpling dough. Stir pretty firmly; mix until just smooth. Add a little extra milk as you go if you need to. Don't go too far; err on the side of too little.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check the chicken. Using tongs, grab one of the drumsticks; with the tip of a paring knife, give it a poke. You want little to no resistance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the chicken set? Awesome. Using a spoon, dollop golf-ball-sized blobs of dough into the pot. Work quickly; go for even coverage. I start at the outside and work my way around toward the middle. Once all the dough is in, put the lid back on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In ten minutes (ish), take the lid back off. The dumplings should be big and poofy and irresistible. A straw or toothpick poked in to the middle should come out clean.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oh my. It's done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serve this in huge bowls -- a dumpling or two and a piece of chicken. Spoon broth over it. Eat this when it's too cold to be outside without a hat and sweater, or when it's raining, or when you need to feel human again. Make it for people you really love. Eat it and be happy.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Ross Donaldson</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>tag:,2013-09-09:skillet.gastove.com/2013-09-09_chicken_and_dumplings_whatever_you.html</guid><category>Family</category><category>Casseroles</category><category>Unborkable</category></item></channel></rss>